בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ביצה ב' עמוד א'.
Beitzah bet amud alef.
We start actually at the beginning of, we begin a new מסכת.
masechet.
So let me tell you a few things about the מסכת. masechet.
First of all, according to some ראשונים, Rishonim, although obviously in the
ancient world, books were named after their first word, hence the name
of פרשיות parshiyot and the name of the ספרים Sfarim in the
חומש Chumash and so on, and therefore this is named ביצה Beitzah
because that's the first word. Nevertheless, in the name, there were other
names as well, and the ראשונים Rishonim sometimes call this מסכת יום
טוב, Masechet Yom Tov, because really the whole מסכת, masechet, it's a
short מסכת, masechet, but it all deals with aspects of יום טוב.
Yom Tov. The first משנה, mishna, the first פרק ביצה perek Beitzah
deals a lot with מוקצה, muktzah, and מוקצה muktzah is sort of
scattered throughout the גמרא. Gemara. A lot of it is in שבת,
Shabbat, but a high concentration is in the first פרק. perek. The
second פרק perek begins with the discussion of עירוב תבשילין Eruv Tavshilin
actually, but gets into a lot of other like דרבננס d'rabanans that
are, you know, that are applied on יום טוב. Yom Tov. The
third פרק perek starts with issues that relate to actually the מלאכות,
melachot, what things are מותר mutar on יום טוב, Yom Tov, because
you know, יום טוב Yom Tov you can do מלאכה אוכל נפש.
melacha ochel nefesh. And then as it continues, the fourth and the
fifth פרק, perek, a lot of different particularly דרבננס d'rabanans around the
issues of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it's a lot about יום
טוב, Yom Tov, and not about חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, that's a
different מסכת, masechet, that's מועד קטן. Moed Katan. This is about יום
טוב Yom Tov and מוקצה muktzah a lot in the beginning. And
the other thing that's really worth mentioning right at the outset is
that there's an enormous amount of מחלוקת בית הלל ובית שמאי. machloket
Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai. The משנה mishna is, you know, you'll see
string after, you know, משנה mishna after משנה, mishna, strings of משניות,
mishnayot, which is just, here's what בית הלל Beit Hillel says, here's
what בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, here's what בית הלל Beit Hillel
says, here's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai says. It seems like, you
know, in most מסכתות, masechtot, the primary speakers in the משנה mishna
are תלמידי רבי עקיבא. talmidei Rabbi Akiva. They're like, you know, רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you
know, they're the students of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, which is very
late. I mean, that's one generation before רבי, Rebbi, the משנה's mishna
editor. But בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai, הלל Hillel
and שמאי Shammai were like a hundred years before חורבן הבית. Churban
HaBayit. בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai still when there
was a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash around. So what you're really dealing
with is a lot of very like early-early משניות, mishnayot, not just
early to dates, like it seems like there was almost no editorial
hand here of רבי Rebbi in a lot of these. It's really
just straight and simple בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai debates on these issues.
It's a fascinating question, like why was there so much בית הלל
ובית שמאי Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai in issues of יום טוב Yom
Tov and not like in other areas. I don't really know the
full answer to that, but anyway, I think that's the other really
distinctive part of the מסכת. masechet. Okay, so that's just a few
opening remarks relating to, relating to the מסכת. masechet. Let's get started.
ביצה שנולדה ביום טוב. Beitzah shenol'da b'yom tov. Okay, so what happens
if you have an egg that's born on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
בית שמאי אומרים תאכל ובית הלל אומרים לא תאכל. Beit Shammai omrim
t'achel u'Beit Hillel omrim lo t'achel. בית שמאי Beit Shammai said you
can eat it, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says you cannot eat
it. Why not? Of course, this is going to be the first
discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's for now assume that it's a
question of נולד, nolad, שנולד, she'nolad, which is a type of an
issue of מוקצה. muktzah. It's something that was not set aside or
could not have been set aside from before יום טוב Yom Tov
began, where בית שמאי Beit Shammai is not bothered by that issue,
he says you can eat it, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says
you can't eat it. Now the question is, if it's a מוקצה
muktzah issue, then it should not just be a question of eating,
it should be a question of moving. So, and we will find
in some places that some things maybe you're not allowed to eat
but you still are allowed to move. What is the story here?
So we'll think about that when we get to the גמרא. Gemara.
For now, let's assume that we're saying both, if it was a
מוקצה muktzah issue, that בית שמאי Beit Shammai says not a problem
at all, not only can you move it, you can even eat
it. And בית הלל Beit Hillel says don't eat it, but that
also means don't move it. That's possible. But their primary discussion, you
know, discussion here is about eating, and that's going to be a
question, is this about a מוקצה muktzah type of concern which relates
also to moving, or is it something that's fundamentally about eating, which
is primarily what you would want to do with it anyway. בית
שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, now בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, and
again what I mentioned before about starting, about a lot of debates
of בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai, the first משנה
mishna opens by what clearly was a certain collection of בית הלל
ובית שמאי Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai debates which were joined together because
they all relate to, to יום טוב Yom Tov issues. But again,
this is, it seems almost a little bit random. Let's take a
look, but the other sort of I should say common denominator about
these is not just it's יום טוב, Yom Tov, but it's three
areas in יום טוב Yom Tov where בית שמאי Beit Shammai is
lenient and בית הלל Beit Hillel is strict, which often goes against
what we normally expect. So that's why clearly these were, these three
things were collected together. בית שמאי אומרים שאור בכזית וחמץ בככותבת. Beit
Shammai omrim se'or b'kezayit v'chametz b'kikhotevet. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that
the שאור, se'or, sourdough, yeast, sourdough, the amount that you need to
transgress for owning it is a כזית kezayit worth, is an olive's
worth, which is, and שאור se'or and חמץ, chametz, normal חמץ chametz
is ככותבת, kikhotevet, it's like the size of
a...
So
again בית הלל Beis Hillel is stricter because a כזית K'zayis is
smaller than a ככותבת. K'koseves. בית שמאי אומרים, Beis Shammai omrim, בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says,
I'm sorry, excuse me, השוחט חיה ועוף ביום טוב. Hashochet chaya v'of
b'yom tov. Now let's say one of the things you're allowed to
do on יום טוב Yom Tov is cook, but for us, that's
what we focus on is cooking. We take these chickens or these
steaks out of the refrigerator and take them off of their wrapping
and our only question is putting them on the fire. But for
them, if they wanted to cook and you wanted some really fresh
meat, so you'd go to the backyard and you'd שחט shecht a
chicken on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay? So, or you'd even
שחט shecht a cow. But let's say you שחט shecht a chicken
or a חיה, chaya, you decided you're going to have venison, you
שחט shecht a deer. One of the things you have to do
when is כיסוי הדם. kisuy hadam. Okay, that wouldn't be an issue
for a cow, but it would be an issue for a bird
or a deer. And you did it on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So now, not related to the necessity of eating would be covering
the blood. That's a מצוה mitzvah that you now sort of tangentially
came about, but it's not specifically related, doesn't, it doesn't allow you
to eat, isn't part of the process of eating. So what do
you do? Do you cover the blood or not? So בית שמאי
אומרים, Beis Shammai omrim, יחפור בדקר ויכסה. yachpor b'deker v'yechaseh.
You can actually dig with a, like a shovel, a hoe, or
a shovel and you can cover the blood so with the dirt.
So A, presumably disregarding מוקצה muktzah issues of the dirt which we
saw before, but perhaps even more serious like digging a hole. ובית
הלל אומרים, u'Beis Hillel omrim, לא ישחוט אלא אם כן היה לו
עפר מוכן מבעוד יום. lo yishchot ela im kein haya lo afar
muchan m'be'od yom. Don't שחט shecht unless you already had, you know,
set aside dirt from the day before that you don't have to
dig and it's not מוקצה, muktzah, you set it aside for that
purpose from the day before. By the way, although we tend to
think that, you know, dirt is מוקצה muktzah by its very definition,
it's not true. If you set it aside, it's not an issue.
If you have a sandbox, you can play in a sandbox on
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. The sand is set aside
for play.
What about digging in it?
All right, I mean, you don't really dig a hole in the
sand. I mean there's a bigger problem about putting water in it
and making it into mud and shaping it. Yeah, does the hole
stay? It's a little thing Reuben, in the sand at the beach,
if it's sand I don't think that's an issue. Anyway, but the
problem is water anyway. ומודים u'modim and they agree, okay so anyway
בית הלל Beis Hillel really did not give a, if you think
about it, did not really give a straight answer. He said, okay,
לכתחילה l'chatchilah don't do it. And if you did it, so what
does he say? So the next clause says ומודים שאם שחט שיחפור
בדקר ויכסה, u'modim she'im shachat she'yachpor b'deker v'yechaseh, that they agree that
if you שחט shechted that you can dig with a shovel. So
the simple read of this משנה mishna is that their only debate
is whether לכתחילה l'chatchilah you're allowed to do it if you don't
have it prepared. But if you actually did it, everybody agrees that
you're allowed to dig to cover it. שאפר כירה מוכן הוא. she'afar
kiro muchan hu. Now this last line opens with a שין, shin,
because, but it seems completely not, yeah, not connected. It says everybody
agrees you can dig and cover it with a shovel because the
ashes from your, from your oven are מוכן. muchan. מוכן muchan is
the opposite of מוקצה. muktzah. So meaning those are not מוקצה. muktzah.
Okay, so that's all fascinating, which obviously implies the idea like oh
if you wanted to use the ashes from your oven that's a
good alternative because that's not considered to be מוקצה. muktzah. But then
why are you allowed to dig with the shovel and why not
just say use the ashes of your oven? The simple read of
it is again, the grammar is funny, is that the ashes, it's
sort of saying, you know, either have the dirt pre-dug or if
you've got אפר efer use that. But if you don't have any
of those alternatives then go ahead and dig. Interesting question why אפר
efer would be, why ashes, you know, of the oven would be
considered מוכן. muchan. When did they become ashes? Before יום טוב Yom
Tov or on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Because you can obviously be
having a fire on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So that's an interesting
question as well. All of this to be explored. As you see,
two out of the three cases, you know, have definitely strong מוקצה
muktzah types of concerns or נולד nolad types of concerns, although the
digging obviously raises other issues as well. Yes.
Perhaps we'll get to this but you were mentioning saying you couldn't
set aside the אפר. efer. Is that because it's like not there
because I have in my mind alright I know this chicken is
going... Yeah, so you can't really
do הכנה hachana on נולד, nolad, because the whole part of נולד
nolad is that it didn't exist beforehand. But we'll talk about that
a little bit more. Actually we'll see a minute in the גמרא
Gemara and I'll mention something relevant that תוספות Tosfos brings in. So
let's take a look now in the גמרא. Gemara. במאי עסקינן? b'mai
askinan? What are we talking about? אילימא בתרנגולת עומדת לאכילה. ileima b'tarnigoles
omedes l'achilah.
If you say, meaning what is the case of this, of this
hen that is, has an egg that the egg could possibly probably
be problematic? If it's about a, a hen that is set aside
for eating, meaning what why are you raising all of these chickens
and hens, are you planning on turning them into meat, are you
planning on having eggs? So, and the גמרא Gemara assumes that you
would obviously have different, you could say you haven't made up your
mind yet, but you know the גמרא Gemara assumes that you would
have different intentions and maybe treat them differently. I mean we know
now in the whole, you know, industry of egg production and meat
production I mean they really have everything you know I mean it's
whatever
it's troubling to even talk about
how... Can you say inhumane about animals, but anyway how inhumane it
is, but they obviously have them, you know, if they're going for
eggs then they have them in a very particular setting in order
to, you know, produce eggs, and if they have an, you know,
for meat they have a very different type of a setting. So
the גמרא Gemara assumes that at that you also would have a
different designation and know what you're planning on using it for. So
what type of a hen are we talking about? Yes?
Is that—or is it just saying the egg is part
of what you eat in the chicken?
Well, that is what it's going to say. You eat the chicken
or you're
going to eat the egg, but does it—? Yeah, yeah, that is
what it's going to say, but it's going to say the status
of the egg depends on what you were planning on doing with
the chicken, and which assumes that you have a plan. They've taken
for granted that you would divide your chickens based on the egg
producers and the ones that will be eventually turned into meat. So
במאי עסקינן, Bamai askinan, what type of cases are we talking about?
אילימא בתרנגולת עומדת לאכילה, Elima b'tarnegolet omedet l'achila, a hen that's set
aside or standing for eating, meaning that you're planning on using it
for food. So מאי טעמא דבית הלל, mai ta'ama d'Beit Hillel, what
would be the reason to be strict about the egg? Here, as
was just said, אוכלא דאפרש הוא, uchla d'afrush hu, it's just food
that's separated from food. Meaning the whole chicken is basically like, you
know, a, like הלכתית, halachically, it's unshechted food, but it's food. Unprepared
food. Okay, and then this egg was born to it. That's a
piece of food that came out of a piece of food. So
you know, why should that be a problem? So אלא, ella, I
got to tell you, I think I did this once before when
we did something else similar in the דף יומי, Daf Yomi, there
was a great Far Side cartoon with like, you know, Farmer Brown
surprises the animals in the barn and like they're all sitting around
this diagram of a person and his, you know, they're like these
different sections and it's cut into like different cuts, like this is
the choice meat and this is the loin.
So anyway, so that's what it is. You're looking at this chicken
and it's a piece of food. Here's the breast, here's the thigh,
here's the this, here's the wings. Okay, so it's a piece of
food. So this is a piece of food that separates from another
piece of food. Why should it be considered something new? There's nothing
new about it. Although you didn't see the egg before, conceptually it's
just a piece of, it's like a leg fell off. Why should
it be a problem?
אלא בתרנגולת—and Ella b'tarnegolet again remember that on יום טוב Yom Tov
the chicken is considered food because you can שחט shecht it. None
of this would be true on שבת, Shabbat, but on יום טוב
Yom Tov you could שחט shecht the chicken. So the chicken is
unprepared food. It is not considered מוקצה. muktza. It's considered something that
you have access to, that you could use. So why is it
a problem?
אלא בתרנגולת עומדת לגדל ביצים. Ella b'tarnegolet omedet l'gadel beitzim. We're talking
about a hen that is set aside for laying eggs. So therefore
then it itself is—is מוקצה. muktza. It's not considered something that I
have reason to be using on—even on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right?
It's just there, it's an egg machine. So I have no use
for it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the egg is something
that came from something that was מוקצה muktza and the egg is
something new. So why should it be—so so that's true. That explains
why it's a problem. So then מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? mai ta'ama
d'Beit Shammai? What's בית שמאי's Beit Shammai reasoning that says it's okay?
מוקצה היא. Muktza hi. It's מוקצה. muktza. And shouldn't בית שמאי Beit
Shammai agree that there's a מוקצה muktza problem, right? It comes from
something that is not—that was itself מוקצה, muktza, presumably this is an
extension of it and this is מוקצה muktza as well. So the
גמרא Gemara says ומה קשיא, u'mai kushya, why is it difficult? דילמא
בית שמאי לית להו מוקצה. Dilma Beit Shammai leit lehu muktza. Maybe
בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't hold the whole category of מוקצה. muktza.
So maybe that's exactly the debate, you hold of מוקצה muktza or
not. So גמרא Gemara says no. קסלקא דעתך—we Ka salka dach-tach are
assuming that אפילו מאן דשרי במוקצה, afilu man d'shari b'muktza, even a
person that doesn't hold of the category of מוקצה—right, muktza maybe that's
a shock to you that there could be some תנאים Tannaim that
don't hold of מוקצה—but muktza yes there are.
If—but we assume that somebody even somebody who basically doesn't believe in
the category in the whole הלכה halacha of מוקצה, muktza, so nevertheless
בנולד אסר, b'nolad assar, would still say נולד nolad is a different
story, right? And here it's interesting to take a minute to appreciate
some different keywords that we're going to have. Okay. First let's talk
about this pair of words which is מוכן muchan and מוקצה. muktza.
Okay. Now מוכן muchan means that it is set aside from before
שבת. Shabbat. מוקצה muktza is the opposite. מוקצה muktza is sort of
pushed away, off limits. Okay, you could say הוקצה huktza set aside
also. הוקצה למצוותו. huktza l'mitzvato. But מוקצה muktza also—but מוכן muchan means
that you're preparing it for use. מוקצה muktza often means that you're
designating it or pushing it away, designating it as something you don't
want to be using. Okay, now there's a huge gap between מוקצה
muktza and מוכן, muchan, which is everything else in the world, right?
There's the things that I sort of know that I'm planning on
using and I basically or maybe implicitly assume I'm going to be
using on שבת, Shabbat, right? My silverware, my plates and my food
and my clothes and all the types of things that I would
normally expect to use. That's מוכן. muchan. Then there are the types
of things that I am מקצה maktze and that I push away.
And what are those types of things? Those are things like you
know
first of all things that I can't use on שבת, Shabbat, you
know my matches, my money, things that I don't want to handle
because they're very fragile, my Ming vase, you know, my... Picasso hanging
up in my living room. So these are the types of things
that like I assume off-hand, off-limits, I don't want to use either
in general or you know or ערלה Orlah has cases about you're
drying food out on the roof, maybe not related to שבת Shabbos
and יום טוב, Yom Tov, these things are things that are like
off-limits, you know, I don't generally want to be handling them or
maybe they're off-limits because you can't handle them on שבת Shabbos or
יום טוב Yom Tov like a chicken, a hen that's around to
lay eggs is מוקצה muktzeh because you don't want to because you
you have no purpose of handling it, it's an egg layer which
means you have no reason to be handling it, right, on on
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. So those are the things
that are מוקצה. muktzeh. Then there's but there's a huge gap, there's
everything else in the world, right, that is not implicitly planned on
being used and not implicitly being pushed off from use, right? So
what's the הלכה halacha about that? Do you need something to actively
be מוכן muchan or something only a problem when it's מוקצה? muktzeh?
That's an issue we're going to get to throughout and we'll get
to a little bit when we turn to the עמוד ב. Amud
Beis. Now you have a new category which is called נולד. nolad.
נולד nolad is something which is like brand new, didn't exist before.
So what גמרא Gemara is saying is the following thing: I might
not hold that any of this stuff, I might not hold that
there's a problem at all because even stuff that basically I have
assumed I'm not going to use or implicitly or explicitly pushed off,
I put it up on the roof, this fruit to dry out
and I'm basically assuming hands off until it's done with the process,
nevertheless, at the end of the day, it's all, you know, objects
under my under my control and I in theory could why would
I ever not you know want to restrain myself from using anything,
right, you know, מלוא הארץ וכבשוה? milu haaretz vekivshuha? I have control
over my entire environment, so maybe implicitly, even if I'm מוקצה muktzeh
it, it's not really something that is considered to be off-limits, something
that is not accessible to me. But something that gets created, that's
brand new, that didn't exist before שבת Shabbos began, that is something
that you cannot say was ever in the realm of something that
when שבת Shabbos began it was theoretically able to be used. Okay,
and therefore, the idea of saying of saying נולד nolad is a
problem in a way, you know, is that you need the things
to be when שבת Shabbos began to be at least in theory
I could have planned to have used this on שבת. Shabbos. Something
that so even things that are מוקצה muktzeh in theory they were
under my control, but something that's נולד nolad doesn't fall into that
category at all, and therefore the גמרא Gemara is saying even if
you don't hold of מוקצה, muktzeh, we assume you're going to feel
that נולד nolad is a problem. Okay, and that's the third idea
which is נולד. nolad. So I think if you look at רש״י,
Rashi, רש״י Rashi says this much more succinctly than I did.
רש״י Rashi says like this,
right on top of, you see the the line on top of
the גיליון הש״ס Gilyon HaShas with like the like the little like
three circles on the far right? So if you go one line
over that, the line starts with the word דאילו de'ilu in רש״י.
Rashi. He says דאילו במוקצה סבירא ליה לא מסיח איניש דעתיה מידי
דחזי ליה. de'ilu bemuktzeh sevira lei lo masach inish dateih midei dechazi
lei. By מוקצה, muktzeh, even if it's something that generally you wouldn't
be touching, like you know your Ming vase or your fruit drying
out, you never in at a deep level want something to be
out of your access. You never fully pushed something off. אבל נולד
לא הוה ידע דהוי דעתיה עילויה. aval nolad lo hava yada dehavai
dateih ilaveih. נולד nolad didn't even exist, so he couldn't even say
theoretically it was something that I could have wanted to use. Okay,
so that's a more serious category that maybe you know even if
you don't hold of מוקצה, muktzeh, נולד nolad is something that completely
did not exist. So the גמרא Gemara says, so we're assuming that
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, קא סלקא דעתך, ka salka daitach, let's read
that again, אפילו מאן דשרי במוקצה בנולד אסר. afilu man deshari bemuktzeh
benolad assar.
Even if you allow מוקצה, muktzeh, נולד nolad you would agree would
be forbidden and we can't understand why בית שמאי Beis Shammai would
allow it on if it was a hen that was set aside
for eggs, that should then be נולד. nolad. So the גמרא Gemara
says so מאי טעמיה דבית שמאי, mai tameih deBeis Shammai, what's בית
שמאי's Beis Shammai's reasoning? So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says which is probably the easiest read of
the משנה, Mishnah, לעולם בתרנגולת העומדת לגדל ביצים, le'olam betarnegolet ha'omedet legadel
beitzim,
it's like we were about assuming just now, it's a hen set
aside for laying eggs. ודאית ליה מוקצה אית ליה נולד ודלית ליה
מוקצה לית ליה נולד, ude'is lei muktzeh is lei nolad udelais lei
muktzeh lais lei nolad, and the one who holds of מוקצה muktzeh
obviously holds נולד nolad is a problem, but you know what, the
one who rejects the idea of מוקצה muktzeh rejects the idea of
נולד nolad as well. Categorically this is always an interesting question, right,
which is if you're debating do you agree in principle but you
disagree in the application or you fundamentally disagree? And the גמרא Gemara
says that we assumed everybody held of נולד, nolad, it meant you
fundamentally agree there's an idea that things have to be ready before
שבת Shabbos begins. You're only debating the application, the particulars. You might
say things that you guys call מוקצה, muktzeh, I don't think that
those really are considered not ready, it's in the world, it's ready.
נולד, nolad, that's not ready. But in principle you agree that there's
a problem an issue of things being ready when שבת Shabbos begins.
What the גמרא Gemara is saying here is no, actually בית שמאי
Beis Shammai rejects it in principle. There is no concept of something
having to be ready from before שבת. Shabbos. And therefore even נולד
nolad is not a problem because they don't hold of מוקצה muktzeh
and they don't hold of נולד, nolad, they don't hold of this
concept at
all. And therefore the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel*,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* is that בית שמאי Beit Shammai
*Beis Shammai* considers this to be נולד Nolad *nolad* and therefore a
problem, I should have set that up wrong, בית הלל Beit Hillel
*Beis Hillel* considers this to be נולד nolad *nolad* and therefore a
problem and he holds of all these categories of נולד *nolad* and
מוקצה Muktzah *Muktzeh*, and בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* doesn't hold
of נולד *nolad*, doesn't hold of מוקצה Muktzah. *Muktzeh*, holds that everything
is totally fine, who cares that it's a new thing. Now, again
I tried to say that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames this as
like as a categorical debate, of course one of the big problems
we're going to get to when we learn this סוגיא *sugya* is
that nobody has statements that sound very categorical, there are always a
lot of exceptions. So for example we're about to introduce an idea
that there's a position of ר' שמעון *Reb Shimon*, this is much
later, this is תלמידי ר' עקיבא *tamidei Reb Akiva*, position of ר'
שמעון *Reb Shimon* that גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ר' שמעון לית ליה
מוקצה Muktzah *Reb Shimon leis lei Muktzeh*, doesn't hold of מוקצה Muktzah
*Muktzeh*. And then you said asterisk, except for the five times when
he does.
So even though the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says that בית שמאי Beit
Shammai *Beis Shammai* doesn't hold of מוקצה Muktzah? *Muktzeh*, doesn't hold of
נולד *nolad*, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* points out a few places where בית
שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* does have some problems with some things
like this. But we're not going to worry about fitting that all
in now, we're going to accept it as a categorical exception. Another
important difference about the idea of נולד *nolad* is a point that
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* makes. Michael sort of asked this question, there are
degrees of נולד *nolad*. There's some things that sort of
the physical matter existed, the physical matter of the egg existed but
it wasn't in our domain, it didn't exist for us. But the
physical matter existed but something new got created out of it, and
that could be a concept of
נולד *nolad*. If you take something that was ink and paper and
you turned it into a newspaper on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*, is that
נולד *nolad*? Because it didn't exist sort of in this form. But
there are ideas of נולד *nolad* where the materials existed but then
something new was created out of it. This idea of the ביצה
Beitzah, *beitzah* is an even more drastic idea of נולד *nolad* because
as far as we're concerned the egg didn't exist yet and now
it comes into existence. This is a lot more drastic and that's
a point that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* makes, just to be aware that
there are different degrees of these things.
Okay if you existence from something that already exists can include changing
the form.
Right,
or it could.
The question is what degree of changing form.
Some for example פוסקים *Poskim* say that water into ice or ice
into water is נולד *nolad*. I don't
think that's a very weak position, it's based whatever I don't want
to go into what it's based on but that's like a simple
state
change. Right, but state change is obviously also different than combining combining
different materials and creating something brand new out of it, so ink
and paper and now you have a book. So anyway there's different
degrees of נולד *nolad*. Yes.
Does it matter that we may have an expectation like when we
used to speak about the dragging through the sand that might create
the problem? So here we might have expected the hen might lay
an egg on.
Oh, so that is a very good question and by the way
that's part of the point that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* makes as well
which is if you actually know that this hen is about to
lay an egg and you say I know it's about to lay
an egg and I make an announcement, I am planning on eating
that egg, I am setting aside the egg that's inside the hen
from before שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*. So excellent question, so it's dealt with
in תוספות *Tosafos* and the basic answer is that that doesn't help
because since it doesn't exist you can't set it aside. It is
funny because it's not visibly accessible to you, it cannot be prepared
and set aside. It's like it doesn't exist so it doesn't matter
sort of what your intention is but again there might be cases
where it does. So it's always these things are not absolute but
תוספות *Tosafos* addresses exactly that. Yes.
Well it sounds like it's the same answer to say if you
שחט shecht *shecht* a chicken
on יום טוב Yom Tov
*Yom Tov* and you cut it open and there's
a whole egg inside, can you eat the egg? Oh, so we're
going to deal with that but if it was a hen that
was set aside let's say a hen that was set yes, but
if it was a hen that was set aside לגבי ביצים *legabeh
beitzim* which is what we're talking about right now then you wouldn't
be able to שחט shechting, *shecht* it
itself would be מוקצה Muktzah *Muktzeh*.
But that's already the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's okay even when
it lays the egg if it was set aside to be eaten
right? So that's the last point that I wanted to make here
which is important about that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's only
considered נולד *nolad* if the hen was set aside to lay eggs
now as opposed to set aside to eat. Now you intuitively might
have thought the opposite. You would have said set aside to lay
eggs I know an egg is coming out, like David says, so
it's not נולד *nolad* I'm planning on eating it. Set aside to
eat, I'm not expecting it to lay eggs, oh that's something new.
So it's a little strange that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes the
reverse. But here's the idea behind what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying. If it is set aside to eat then the egg coming
out is not seen as something different from the chicken. It's like
when it was in the chicken it was part of the food
of the chicken, part of the chicken as a piece of food
and now it's just a piece of food that sort of grew
a little bit or came out a little bit but it's not
like conceptually different although physically you didn't have the egg in front
of you before, it's not something new in terms of this like
real Halachic man, you're going around with these concepts. conceptual categories. So
although physically it's new, conceptually it's not new, it's just a piece
of food that fell off from another piece of food. Whereas if
I have a hen laying machine, although I expect excuse me, an
egg laying machine, although I expect it to produce eggs, an egg
is something different from the machine, right? The machine is there to
make the eggs, and the egg is what it's producing. So this
is conceptually something new and different from the machine that produced it.
Okay, that's sort of the concept behind it, but again, it is
a little surprising. Okay, so let's take a look.
First differentiation between שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov. is when
he speaks about an egg on שבת. Shabbat. Yes, I assume you're
going to eat it raw?
Well, yeah, that's a good question about food that's raw and so
on, but you could eat a raw egg and that would not
be a problem. But שבת Shabbat is a pro so that would
not make it more problematic, but שבת Shabbat is more of a
problem because you couldn't eat it from because in all cases the
hen would be out of your reach because it wouldn't be theoretically
edible on שבת. Shabbat Okay, so now let's continue. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: where are we?
Okay, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai כרבי שמעון. k'Rabbi Shimon. So now
again it's a little bit funny that the גמרא Gemara is making
an association based on תנאים Tanaim that came much later. But for
the גמרא, Gemara the category of those that don't hold of מוקצה
Muktzah is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says רבי שמעון לית ליה
מוקצה. Rabbi Shimon leis lei Muktzah. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai כרבי
שמעון, k'Rabbi Shimon, בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds like
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, ובית הלל u'Beit Hillel כרבי יהודה, k'Rabbi Yehuda,
and בית הלל Beit Hillel, goes like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who
holds of the category of מוקצה. Muktzah Okay, very easy explanation in
the משנה, Mishnah, do you hold of מוקצה Muktzah and נולד or
not? So גמרא says: ומי אמר רב נחמן הכי? u'mi amar Rav
Nachman hachi? Did רב נחמן Rav Nachman really say this, that בית
שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't hold of מוקצה Muktzah and בית הלל Beit
Hillel does? והתנן, ve'hasnan, we have a משנה. Mishnah. בית שמאי אומרים:
Beit Shammai omrim: מטלטלין על השולחן עצמות וקליפין. mataltalin al hashulchan atzamot
u'kelipin. You have the bones left over from your chicken and the
shells left over from your walnut, and now they're on the table.
Are they מוקצה? Muktzah. There's no use for them. Now of course
תוספות says that point the question is are they fit to be
eaten even by dogs? רשי Rashi says no, תוספות says yes, but
they're still considered מוקצה Muktzah because they're not or they might be
considered מוקצה Muktzah because they're not fit to be eaten by humans
at this stage. So what do you do? So בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says you can pick them up, clear off your table, no
problem, pick up the bones. ובית הלל אומרים: u'Beit Hillel omrim: מסלק
את הטבלא כולה ומנערה. mesalek et hatavla kulo u'm'ara. No,
you can take the tablecloth or the table she's talking about like
the tray and shake it out and dump the tray into the
garbage, but you cannot directly handle. Why? Some interesting this is an
idea called טלטול מן הצד, tiltul min hatzad, that by מוקצה Muktzah.
you're allowed to move things indirectly. Now there's a whole range of
why, what defines indirect or when is something just an extension of
your hand, טלטול מן הגוף tiltul min haguf as opposed to טלטול
מן הצד. tiltul min hatzad. Don't worry, we'll get to that. But
the basic idea is you're only handling it indirectly and that gives
you much more latitude. תוספות also תוספות asks what about the issue
of בסיס? basis? You might know this idea that if you keep
something, you put something on a place before שבת Shabbat and it
was there all בין השמשות, bein hashmashot, right? Like say something that
was מוקצה Muktzah, like the candles burning on the candlestick, בסיס לדבר
האסור, basis ledavar ha'asur, the candlestick also becomes מוקצה Muktzah, because they
were a base of support for מוקצה. Muktzah The easiest answer here
is that this stuff wasn't on בין השמשות, bein hashmashot, it got
produced on שבת Shabbat itself. But anyway, that's בית הלל, Beit Hillel
בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's a מוקצה Muktzah problem, move it
indirectly. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says not so. That's perfect, it works
in perfect works in perfectly with our משנה: Mishnah: בית שמאי Beis
Shammai doesn't hold of מוקצה muktzah. and בית הלל Beit Hillel does
hold of מוקצה. muktzah So everything would have been wonderful except along
comes the same רב נחמן Rav Nachman and look what he does.
ואמר רב נחמן: ve'amar Rav Nachman: רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, אנו
אין לנו, anu ein lanu,
we don't hold of like this version of the משנה, Mishnah, the
only version we accept is אלא בית שמאי כרבי יהודה ובית הלל
כרבי שמעון. ella Beit Shammai k'Rabbi Yehuda u'Beit Hillel k'Rabbi Shimon. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai goes like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, בית שמאי is
strict and goes like the position that there is מוקצה, muktzah. and
בית הלל Beit Hillel, goes like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that there
isn't, and basically he reverses the opinions in the משנה. Mishnah. בית
הלל Beit Hillel says that you can remove the bones, and בית
שמאי says you can only indirectly move the table and shake off
the tablecloth, shake out the tray. So רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, you
did yourself in. You explained this משנה Mishnah which you can't switch
around because this משנה Mishnah clearly is קולי בית שמאי וחומרי בית
הלל, kulei Beit Shammai ve'chumrei Beit Hillel, this משנה Mishnah where you
said בית שמאי doesn't hold of מוקצה, muktzah, you had another משנה
Mishnah that supported you by שבת Shabbat? with the bones, and you
reversed it. So how are we supposed to make sense of this?
So let's take a look. אמר לך רב נחמן: amar lach Rav
Nachman: רב נחמן Rav Nachman will say to you, גבי שבת, gabi
Shabbat, by שבת Shabbat, דסתם לן תנא כרבי שמעון, d'stam lan tanna
k'Rabbi Shimon, we have a סתם משנה stam Mishnah relating to שבת
Shabbat, that goes like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that there
is not a מוקצה muktzah problem. What's the משנה Mishnah by שבת?
Shabbat דתנן, detnan, taught in the משנה: Mishnah: מחתכין את הדלועין לפני
הבהמה, m'chatchen et hadelu'in lifnei habehema,
you can chop up raw gourd before animals in order to make
them edible. Now that's not a מוקצה muktzah problem, the gourd was
plucked before whatever, pulled out before שבת, Shabbat. or plucked, goes on
a vine, right? Gourd? Yes. Okay, it was plucked before שבת, Shabbat
but it is a problem you might have thought it's a problem
because it's like you're making something that's not edible in that current
state, by chopping it up you're making it edible, you might have
thought it's a problem, but no, you're allowed to do that, it's
not considered an unnecessary טרחא tircha or another problem of making food,
that's okay to do for your animal.
את הנבילה לפני הכלבים, et haneveilah lifnei haklavim, and this is the
relevant part for us, let's say your animal, your cow drops dead
on Shabbat, okay? Or so the it's it's מוקצה. muktzah You had
no use for your cow on Shabbat, right? You couldn't have שחט'd
shechting it, it wasn't יום טוב. Yom Tov And now what can
you take this dead carcass and chop it up and make dog
meat out of it and feed your dog and feed your animals
on Shabbat? So the משנה Mishnah says yes, it's not bothered with
a מוקצה muktzah problem, okay? Even though clearly this was something that
was not set aside for before Shabbat. So that's a סתם משנה
stam Mishnah that doesn't hold of מוקצה. muktzah, So therefore since that
סתם משנה stam Mishnah doesn't hold of מוקצה, muktzah we're going to
assume and we assume the הלכה halakhah is always like בית הלל,
Beit Hillel so we have to align בית הלל Beit Hillel, with
that position that on Shabbat there's no מוקצה muktzah problem. So מוקים
לה לבית הלל כרבי שמעון, mookim lah leVeit Hillel keRabbi Shimon, so
therefore we say by Shabbat בית הלל Beit Hillel goes like רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, there is no מוקצה muktzah problem, which is consistent
with the סתם משנה. stam Mishnah.
אבל גבי יום טוב, aval gabei Yom Tov, turn the page, wait
a sec, by יום טוב Yom Tov דסתם לן תנא כרבי יהודה,
desatam lan tanna keRabbi Yehuda, there the סתם משנה stam Mishnah by
יום טוב Yom Tov goes like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that there
is a that there is that there is a מוקצה muktzah problem.
Where's a משנה Mishnah by יום טוב Yom Tov that assumes there
is a מוקצה muktzah. problem? דתנן, detnan, we taught in a משנה
Mishnah in ביצה, Beitzah, a משנה Mishnah we're going to see later
on. אין מבקעין עצים מן הקורות, ein mevak'in eitzim min hakorot, if
you have beams that are set aside on a construction site and
now it's middle of יום טוב Yom Tov. and you say you
know what, I didn't prepare enough firewood, let's go to that construction
site, let's assume it's not גזל, gezel, let's go to my construction
site and take some of those perfect beams and use them for
the fire. Nah, I mean that's מוקצה, muktzah. it's מוקצה muktzah set
aside for the construction purposes, so you can't do that, you can't
chop those beams, ולא מן הקורה שנפלה ביום טוב, velo min hakorah
shenafela beYom Tov, or let's say, you know, a roof collapsed on
יום טוב. Yom Tov? Can you now go ahead and use this
beam from the collapsed roof on יום טוב? Yom Tov That's sort
of like the animal that died, right? When יום טוב Yom Tov,
began, it was like, I have no use for the beams that
are part of my roof, but now that it collapsed on יום
טוב, Yom Tov now it's in a usable state, but when יום
טוב Yom Tov, began it wasn't. So that's a מוקצה muktzah problem
and it says don't do it. So we have the animal dying
on Shabbat, no problem. The roof falling in on יום טוב, Yom
Tov problem. So what's the explanation? It must be on Shabbat we
hold of מוקצה muktzah and on יום טוב Yom Tov we don't
hold of I'm sorry, I said that wrong. On Shabbat we don't
hold of מוקצה muktzah and on יום טוב Yom Tov. we do
hold of מוקצה. muktzah So it must be that there's a difference
between Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov So he says therefore, let's
take a look. So by Shabbat the סתם משנה stam Mishnah is
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that holds of that holds of מוקצה.
muktzah I'm sorry, I said that wrong again. Did I say it
wrong? No, I said it right. Oh,
no, excuse me. ביבמות? beYevamot? No, ביום טוב. beYom Tov. ביום טוב,
beYom Tov, not by Shabbat. I'm sorry, I'm confusing myself. Got it.
Let's start again from the top. גבי יום טוב דסתם לן תנא
כרבי יהודה, gabei Yom Tov desatam lan tanna keRabbi Yehuda, by יום
טוב Yom Tov. the סתם משנה stam Mishnah is like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. דתנן אין מבקעין עצים מן הקורות, detnan ein mevak'in eitzim
min hakorot, this is again a משנה Mishnah in ביצה, you don't
chop wood from stuff set aside for like to be, you know,
construction beams, ולא מן הקורה שנשברו ביום טוב, velo min hakorah shenishberu
beYom Tov, and not from a beam that broke. So that משנה
Mishnah holds of מוקצה mukhtzeh. on יום טוב. Yom Tov, So מוקים
לה לבית הלל כרבי יהודה, mookim lah leVeit Hillel keRabbi Yehuda, rather
than saying that the סתם משניות stam Mishnayot are not in agreement,
we're going to assume that the סתם משניות stam Mishnayot are intentionally
סתם stam and therefore are the הלכה. halakhah. And therefore the הלכה
halakhah is, and we also assume the הלכה halakhah is like בית
הלל, Beit Hillel so we see that the הלכה halakhah is that
there is no מוקצה mukhtzeh by Shabbat, there is מוקצה mukhtzeh by
יום טוב, Yom Tov and we're going to adjust בית הלל Beit
Hillel to be in line with that. So our משנה Mishnah that
says by יום טוב בית הלל Yom Tov Beit Hillel holds a
problem, that there is a problem of a ביצה שנולדה ביום טוב,
beitzah shenolada beYom Tov, that's where בית הלל Beis Hillel holds a
problem, fine. That's the משנה Mishnah about the beams falling in on
יום טוב Yom Tov and יום טוב Yom Tov is like בית
it there is a problem of מוקצה. mukhtzeh, By Shabbat we have
this issue about the animal that died and the נבילה. neveilah. It
tells us that there is not a problem of מוקצה mukhtzeh. on
Shabbat. So this debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel veBeit
Shammai about picking up the bones on the table, we're going to
reverse the positions to get בית הלל Beis Hillel consistent with the
הלכה halakhah that there isn't a problem of מוקצה mukhtzeh, on Shabbat.
So now we have to ask, what is this bizarre idea that
there's a problem of מוקצה muktzeh. on יום טוב Yom Tov and
not on Shabbat? Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא
says one minute, ומאי שנא ביום טוב דסתם לן כרבי יהודה, umai
shna beYom Tov desatam lan keRabbi Yehuda, why on יום טוב Yom
Tov is the סתם משנה stam Mishnah like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that there is a problem, the משנה Mishnah about the beams falling
in, and and not I'm sorry, I skipped a line. מאי שנא,
mai shna, the גמרא says מכדי, michdi, let's take a look, four
lines from the top. מאן סתמיה למתניתין, man stamih lematnitin, who is
the one that chose which משניות Mishnayot to make anonymous and therefore
to have the weight of authority? רבי, Rebbe, it was רבי יהודה
הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. מאי שנא בשבת דסתם לן כרבי שמעון, mai
shna beShabbat desatam lan keRabbi Shimon, why by Shabbat did he choose
to have the anonymous משנה Mishnah embody the position of רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and say that it was not a problem when the
animal becomes dies on Shabbat? ומאי שנא ביום טוב, umai shna beYom
Tov, and why in יום טוב Yom Tov דסתם לן כרבי יהודה,
desatam lan keRabbi Yehuda, did he make the סתם משנה stam Mishnah
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and say that on on יום טוב
Yom Tov? it is a problem by the case of the beams
falling? Why is it not a problem on Shabbat and there is
a problem on יום טוב? Yom Tov Why did רבי Rebbe adopt
opposing positions? So the גמרא says like, אמרי, Amri, שבת דחמירא Shabbat
de-chamira לא אתו לזלזולי בה. lo atu le-zilzulei bah. שבת Shabbat is
strict,
so people are not going to make it, treat it lightly. דסתם
לן כרבי שמעון, De-stam lan ke-Rabbi Shimon, he פסק paskened like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon דמקל de-meikel regarding מוקצה. muktzeh You don't need to
have מוקצה muktzeh on שבת. Shabbat You treat שבת Shabbat. seriously enough.
יום טוב דקיל ואתי לזלזולי ביה, Yom Tov de-kil ve-atu le-zilzulei beih,
יום טוב Yom Tov. is more lenient. You can do all these
types of things. Besides it's more lenient that the punishment is not
like חייב מיתה, chayav misa, it's only a לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh.
But also you have a lot of latitude. You're שחט, you're cooking,
so there's a lot of reasons why you might a little bit,
I mean for us, you know, we do such so little even
on יום טוב. Yom Tov Like I'm always having this debate with
my wife which is like, you know, she cooks all the food
for יום טוב Yom Tov. ahead of time. I say, you're allowed
to cook on יום טוב. Yom Tov I say, I'm going to
buy some steaks, put them in the fridge, come יום טוב Yom
Tov I'm going to grill them up. So and I think ספרדים
Sefardim like I know I hear like on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
they have like barbecues, right? Okay. So imagine that not only were
you doing that, you were going out to your field and שחט
your chickens, right? So obviously on יום טוב Yom Tov. you have
a lot more latitude, so there's a more likelihood you'll forget the
קדושת היום, kedushat ha-yom, you'll forget the sense of restriction. So therefore
we're going to have מוקצה and limit the types of objects you
can interact with, which makes a lot of sense. If you're very
conscious of the objects you're interacting with, you're much more conscious of
the fact that it is יום טוב. Yom Tov. So therefore יום
טוב דקיל ואתי לזלזולי ביה, Yom Tov de-kil ve-atu le-zilzulei beih, סתם
לן כרבי יהודה stam lan ke-Rabbi Yehuda דמחמיר. de-machmir. Now I want
to say two things about this, about this issue. First of all,
right, the גמרא is almost a little bit aware that
or what it's framing it as is not like there is a
תנא tanna out there that holds of these contradictory opinions, whatever, these
different approaches from שבת Shabbat. and יום טוב. Yom Tov רבי Rebbe
made a conscious choice to say, "I'm going to פסק, pasken, you
know, like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon on שבת Shabbos. and not have
מוקצה, and I'm going to פסק pasken like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
on יום טוב Yom Tov and have מוקצה." So it was רבי
Rebbe who decided to have this split vote. So that's pretty funny
because then presumably בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי never split
their vote either, right? It was only רבי Rebbe who finally decided
to have this interesting split vote. But still, if we want בית
הלל Beis Hillel. at the end of the day to go according
to הלכה, halacha, we're going to reverse who said what to make
בית הלל Beis Hillel consistent with הלכה. halacha. It seems very manipulative,
right? Why not just assume רבי, Rebbe, you know, רבי Rebbe had
a split vote, it wasn't earlier? But we wouldn't want רבי Rebbe
to פסק pasken against בית הלל. Beis Hillel But again, did the
גמרא really think that בית הלל Beis Hillel held the opposite position
or was it just we have to do that? We have to
reassign בית הלל to make it line up with the הלכה. halacha.
So that's like one interesting question. Now if you think that sounds
too manipulative, I want to read to you a רש"י Rashi which
is רבי Rebbe deciding to make a משנה mishna סתם משנה. stam
mishna. Right? What does it mean that he chose to make it
a סתם משנה stam mishna that it should be have the weight
of authority? So if you take a look, like I would say,
okay, by doing that he communicated to us, "This is the position
that I hold of," and maybe the fact that he held of
it gave it weight that the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פסק paskened
a certain way, and that's becomes accepted and canonized and so on.
Then that's where it carries weight, but we all know it's the
opinion of the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. רבי Rebbe is communicating to
us his opinion by deciding which משנה mishna to make סתם stam
to make anonymous. But look at what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi
says something which is harder to get your head around. He says,
four lines down in the narrow lines, "מאן סתם לן למתניתין? Man
stam lan le-masnisin? Who is the one that decided which משניות mishnayos
to make סתם? stam? רבי שסידר המשנה, Rebbe she-sider ha-mishna, רבי Rebbe
arranged the משנה. mishna. Notice by the word arrange because a lot
of the משניות mishnayos pre-existed, and a lot of what most of
what he was doing or almost all the משניות mishnayos pre-existed was
just arranging them. וחזה דברי חכם וישרו בעיניו, Ve-chaza divrei chacham ve-yashru
be-einav, when he when one of the when one of the opinions
seemed correct in his eyes, שנהם סתם, shanam stam, he taught it
anonymously, ולא הזכיר שם אומרו עליהם, ve-lo hizkir shem omro aleihem, did
not mention who the author was on them, כדי שלא ישנו מפי
יחיד, kedei she-lo yishnu mipi yachid, it should not be attributed to
a single opinion, just one person's opinion, ויראו כאילו נשנו מפי המרובים
ויעשו כמותם, ve-yeira'u ke-illu nishnu mipi ha-merubim ve-ya'asu kemosam, to give the
impression that this was a consensus opinion and everybody would follow it."
So not just to communicate to us how he פסק. paskened. He
did it to make us think it was a consensus opinion. I
don't know what to say about that. Like you're duping, just basically
duping us, you know? Maybe you could reinterpret רש"י Rashi to say
that he gave it the voice of consensus. We all understood it
wasn't a consensus, but he gave it that voice. But anyway, it's
a quite strange רש"י Rashi that seems like רבי Rebbe was trying
to deceive us that that this was a consensus opinion. Yes?
There is אמוראים Amoraim discussion about that משנה mishna in שבת. Shabbos,
Yes, and if I remember right, they rule with רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon.
Well, right, there is a question about how in the end we
rule, but now we're working within רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So let's
just review what we've said. We basically have said that רב נחמן
Rav Nachman takes an easy explanation of the משנה. mishna. בית שמאי
doesn't hold of מוקצה, בית הלל does. It actually is consistent with
other משניות mishnayos in שבת. Shabbos, About בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* not
holding of מוקצה *Muktzeh* and בית הלל *Beit Hillel* holding of it,
but because רבי *Rebbe* פוסק *paskens* differently in שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* and
יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* also rearranged
the position by שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* to have this consistent with the
פסק *psak* of רבי *Rebbe*, that by יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom
Tov* there is מוקצה *Muktzeh* and by שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* not. But
in terms of explaining our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, it is really quite
simple: it is a debate of whether there is מוקצה *Muktzeh*. בית
שמאי *Beit Shammai* says no, בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says yes. Maybe
it is specific, maybe יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* is different
than שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*, but at least by יום טוב Yom Tov.
*Yom Tov*, that is the debate. Let us see where the גמרא
*Gemara* goes on. It says like this: במאי
אוקימתא *Bemai okimta*? What did you say that our משנה *Mishnah* is
talking about? בתרנגולת העומדת לגדל ביצים *Betarnegolet ha'omedet legadel beitzim*, a chicken
that is out to grow eggs and that is set aside for
growing eggs, for laying eggs. ומשום מוקצה *Umishum muktzeh*, and it is
a problem of מוקצה *Muktzeh*, and that is the debate. אי הכי
*Ei hachi*, if so, says the גמרא *Gemara*, עד דמיפלגי בביצה *Ad
d'miflegi b'beitzah*, why are they debating just the egg? ליפלגו בתרנגולת *Liflegu
b'tarnegolet*, debate the hen itself? If you chose to eat the hen,
that is also a מוקצה *Muktzeh* problem, and say בית שמאי *Beit
Shammai* says fine and בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says no good. גמרא
*Gemara* says no: להודיעך כוחן דבית שמאי *Lehodi'acha kochan deBeit Shammai*, to
tell you the strength of בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* position, דבנולד שרי
*De'benolad sharei*, he is so lenient, not only does he allow the
hen, which is only a מוקצה *Muktzeh* problem, he even allows the
egg, which is נולד *Nolad*. That is how lenient he is. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says: וליפלגו בתרנגולת להודיעך כוחן דבית הלל *Veliflegu b'tarnegolet
lehodi'acha kochan deBeit Hillel*, דבמוקצה אסרי *De'bemuktzeh asrei*. So tell us the
case of the hen to show us how strong בית הלל *Beit
Hillel* is, that not only do they forbid the egg, they forbid
the hen. So the egg is a bigger חידוש chiddush *chiddush* to
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*, they are so lenient they allow the egg,
but tell us the hen which is a bigger חידוש *chiddush* to
בית הלל *Beit Hillel*, they are so strict they do not even
allow the hen. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: וכי תימא כוח דהיתרא
עדיף *Vechi teima koach deheteira adif*, you will say no, the power
to say something is permissible is greater than to say it is
forbidden. Like רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, anybody can say it is forbidden, 'Oh,
I do not know if you should do it or not, better
not to do it.' So it is always easier to say it
is אסור *assur*. It takes real conviction and real belief in your
position to say that I am going to allow it, I do
not think it is a problem. כוח דהיתרא עדיף *Koach deheteira adif*.
So we would rather tell you how powerful בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*
position is, they even allow the egg. כוח דהיתרא עדיף
*Koach deheteira adif*. I am sorry about this, it is always easier
to say it is אסור *assur*. Rabbi Love tells a story about,
I forget who it was, but some big
פוסק *posek* in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, there is this book out of his
פסקים *psakim* like one-line answers. Anyway, so somebody asked him: אם מותר
לשחק כדורסל בשבת *Im mutar lesachek kadursal b'Shabbat*, can you play basketball
on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*? So he said: מה זה כדורסל *Ma zeh
kadursal*? What is this? זה משחק כזה ששמים כדור בתוך סל *Zeh
mis'chak kazeh she'samim kadur betoch sal*. So he said: יותר טוב לשים
את הכדור בתוך הסל לפני
השבת *Yoter tov lasim et hakadur betoch hasal lifnei haShabbat*. All right,
anyway, so why not tell us the principle of, so maybe that
is why you say the egg to show you that בית שמאי
*Beit Shammai* is so lenient that they even allow the egg. So
that is why we are focusing on the egg. גמרא *Gemara* says
no, I am not satisfied. וניפלגו בתרווייהו *V'niflegu betarveihu*, why not still
debate both of them? It would not be a lot of effort
to include the hen in the discussion. It is not a new
thing to point out. All you have to do is just modify
the משנה *Mishnah* a little bit. Why not say the following? תרנגולת
העומדת לגדל ביצים והיא וביצתה *Tarnegolet ha'omedet legadel beitzim vehi uveitzatah*, it
is your hen set aside for eggs, it and its egg. בית
שמאי אומרים תאכל ובית הלל אומרים לא תאכל *Beit Shammai omrim techal
uBeit Hillel omrim lo techal*. Now,
of course it is a lot more words. ביצה שנולדה ביום טוב
*Beitzah shenolada b'Yom Tov* is three words. This is a lot more
words. But the point is, it is not really a different scenario.
So just discuss the hen itself. If it was really about מוקצה
*Muktzeh*, we would be discussing the hen itself. So now the גמרא
*Gemara* is going to abandon רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*. Now, I have
to tell you that is a pretty weak answer to abandon what
is a pretty straightforward interpretation. We see בית הלל *Beit Hillel* and
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* debate about מוקצה *Muktzeh*. It is a pretty
straightforward interpretation. One of the things that it seems like the סתם
*Stam* is doing is that there are a lot of interpretations of
the משנה *Mishnah*. And rather than just saying רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*
said this is what is going on, רבה *Rabbah* says this is
going on, יוסף *Yosef* says this is going on, it is going
to give us a reason why we have to now look for
another explanation. So it says, רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* does not work
so well, it should have mentioned the hen, let us try to
get another explanation of the משנה *Mishnah*. But it is really a
weak reason to reject a very reasonable, strong reading of the משנה
*Mishnah*. Let us see what the גמרא *Gemara*, but the גמרא *Gemara*
is going to use that as a way now to get to
another read of the משנה *Mishnah*. So read number one is a
hen set aside for eggs and that it is an issue of
for laying eggs and it is an issue of מוקצה *Muktzeh*. Yes.
So when the סתם *Stam* does that, it is part of its
agenda perhaps to introduce these categories that you would not have thought.
Exactly, particularly in an opening סוגיא *Sugya*. Right, and particularly in an
opening סוגיא *Sugya* in particular. But here again, sometimes what you see
is in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, this whole סוגיא *Sugya* could be three
lines. It could be רב נחמן אמר *Rav Nachman amar*, בתרנגולת העומדת
לגדל ביצים ומשום מוקצה *betarnegolet ha'omedet legadel beitzim umishum muktzeh*, רבה *Rabbah*
is going to say X, so and so, somebody else is going
to say Y, it will be the whole thing will be
just... move on to the next idea. So, but you're right, we're
trying to present all of the ideas. Rav Nachman seems to be
a very straightforward view. Let's see where the גמרא goes next. Tells
like this. So גמרא says like this. אמר רבא Amar Rava לעולם
בתרנגולת העומדת לאכילה. le'olam betarnigoles haomedes laachilah. Let's say, let's go back
where
the hen was set aside in order to be eaten and therefore
it's not נולד because it's just like a piece of food coming
from a piece of food.
So what's the problem? וביום טוב שחל להיות אחר השבת עסקינן. ubeyom
tov shechal lihyos achar hashabbos askinan. Actually we're talking about a special
case or the special case is the reason behind all of this.
What's the special case? When יום טוב Yom Tov comes after
שבת. Shabbos, ומשום הכנה. Umishum hachanah. Now the problem is that it
isn't prepared. What does that mean? וכסבר רבא Vechasavar Rava and here's
that idea of הכנה hachanah I mentioned before,
רבא Rava holds כל ביצה דמיתילדא האידנא נגמרה לה מאתמול. kol beitzah
demisvalda haidana nigmrah lah me'esmol. So it was already ready to come
out yesterday.
And let's just line up all these things and then I'll unpack
it. ורבא לטעמיה, VeRava litaimei, רבא Rava goes according to his reasoning,
דאמר רבא deamar Rava מאי דכתיב mai dechsiv והיה ביום השישי והכינו
את אשר
יביאו. vehayah bayom hashishi vehechinu es asher yavi'u. It'll be on the
sixth day they will prepare what they're going to do, right? The
Torah had already said את אשר תאפו אפו ואת אשר תבשלו בשלו,
es asher tofu efu ve'es asher tebashlu bashelu, right? It's already said
do all your cooking, do all your baking, so why do you
have to again say prepare? It already said do all your cooking
and baking. So to tell you חול מכין לשבת, chol mechin leShabbos,
weekday has to prepare for שבת, Shabbos, וחול מכין ליום טוב, vechol
mechin leYom Tov, and a weekday you have to prepare for יום
טוב. Yom Tov ואין יום טוב מכין לשבת, Ve'ein Yom Tov mechin
leShabbos, יום טוב Yom Tov cannot be preparing for שבת, Shabbos ואין
שבת מכינה ליום טוב, ve'ein Shabbos mechina leYom Tov, and שבת Shabbos
cannot prepare for יום טוב. Yom Tov So what does all this
mean? So if it meant you actually doing the cooking and so
on, so, you know, that's obviously you can't like cook on שבת
Shabbos for יום טוב. Yom Tov. You don't need רבא Rava to
tell me that. The חידוש here is about something like this, which
is it was prepared but you weren't the one that prepared it.
You know, you weren't like violating שבת Shabbos, in order to make
something for יום טוב Yom Tov, or violating יום טוב Yom Tov
to make something for שבת. Shabbos No, it was just this thing
that was growing naturally in the chicken, the egg that was ready
to be laid. But what you find is not a problem that
you did some act of violation, but the reality is this egg,
if you want to use it on שבת, Shabbos it has to
be prepared from beforehand. And it cannot have יום טוב Yom Tov.
being the time when this egg became now ready to be used
for שבת, Shabbos, it has to be ready on a preceding weekday.
It's a hard idea to get your head around because as רש''י
Rashi points out, you would think if there's a problem for יום
טוב Yom Tov. preparing for שבת, Shabbos the bigger problem should be
for שבת Shabbos preparing for Sunday. So how can I eat an
egg that's laid on Sunday? I shouldn't have something that שבת Shabbos
prepared for Sunday. But again, the problem isn't, the way רש''י Rashi
frames it, that somehow the קדושה kedushah of שבת Shabbos was violated
because this egg was being prepared. Then it would obviously be a
bigger problem if it was prepared on שבת, Shabbos you know, somehow
that violated שבת Shabbos that the egg was being prepared for Sunday.
It all happens automatically. The problem is not a sense of violation,
the problem is, the way רש''י says it, is that the Torah
gives חשיבות, chashivus, weight, to the סעודה seudah of שבת and the
סעודה seudah of יום טוב. Yom Tov. And therefore, for something to
be able, and this רבא Rava might be talking specifically about things
about eating, and remember the egg, the משנה did not talk about
moving the egg, it talks about eating the egg. So the point
is if you want to eat something for שבת, you want to
eat something for יום טוב, you have to, you know, it's like
רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik had this beautiful line, he said in America
we have a lot of שומרי שבת, shomrei Shabbos, what we don't
have enough of is שומר ערב שבת. shomer erev Shabbos. You know,
what ערב שבת erev Shabbos is like, you know, what it means
to really see שבת as coming and prepare for it. So if
you want something to be part of your שבת meal, it has
to be prepared not even by you actively, but
ready objectively from before on a weekday. And it can't have been
ready even on a יום טוב that precedes שבת or שבת that
precedes יום טוב.
Weekday is when you do things, when things have to be done
and ready to be used for a meal of שבת and יום
טוב. So that's the idea even though it's not about you doing
an act, even though it's about something passively. This is called הכנה
דרבא, hachanah deRava, which is רבא Rava sees this based on a
biblical verse, on a פסוק. pasuk. It might even be a דאורייתא
d'Oraisa according to רבא, Rava, but it's not the same as all
the rabbinic area of מוקצה. Exactly what the overlap is and how
far he would extend it, but this again has a real focus
on the סעודה seudah of שבת and יום טוב. Maybe it's only
a problem of eating, maybe he would say you'd be able to
move the egg, maybe it's only an eating problem because it's about
the סעודה, seudah, and it is this idea that things you're going
to use, now look, to some degree when I put on the
board מוכן, muchan, a lot of מוקצה is you have to prepare
things from beforehand. So the question becomes, well is רבא Rava saying
that all categories of מוקצה are הכנה hachanah and so on? So
again, not necessarily. This could be specifically in areas of food and
the meal and preparing for it, and that has to be ready
from the weekday, and this egg wasn't ready. This egg gets is
ready. the day before it's laid, and if יום טוב *Yom Tov*
preceded שבת *Shabbat* or שבת *Shabbat* preceded יום טוב *Yom Tov*, it
wasn't ready on a weekday, and for him, that is a real
problem.
Essentially it's one day.
One day. Yes. Charlie, you had a question.
Yes, so if you can't prepare on a יום טוב *Yom Tov*
for שבת *Shabbat* and it's biblical, how can an עירוב *eruv*...
Okay, that's an excellent question. So תוספות *Tosafot* asks that. So תוספות
*Tosafot* says, if even by it happening by itself, you can't prepare,
how can we cook from יום טוב *Yom Tov* to שבת *Shabbat*?
And תוספות *Tosafot* says, and this ties into the point I said
before, there are degrees of, like the same way there are degrees
of נולד *nolad*, there are degrees of מוכן *muchan*. If the raw
materials are all in front of you, and they're just like lacking
preparation, you know, now of course that's a little funny because the
פסוקים *pesukim* talk about את אשר תאפו אפו ואת אשר תבשלו בשלו
*et asher tofu tofu ve'et asher tevashlu bashelu*, but תוספות *Tosafot* nevertheless
he says, I'll read you in תוספות *Tosafot*, he says, he says,
שאינו מחוסר רק תיקון בעלמא ומעיקרא הוה חזי ליה *she'eino mechusar rak
tikkun be'alma vemeikara havah chazi lei*, it was there, you
all you need to do was fix it up, as opposed to
the egg which came totally brand new, right, which is sounding again
like this type of a נולד *nolad* issue. But you are right,
it's a little bit strange, because the whole פסוקים *pesukim* are about
cooking and so on beforehand and now we're saying, no, this idea
really, you know, is an idea of it just being existing beforehand,
being prepared in the sense of existing beforehand. So it really limits
the idea of רבא *Rava*, but it's a very good question. The
other thing I should point out is that who mentioned יום טוב
*Yom Tov*? The פסוקים *pesukim* talk about preparing before שבת *Shabbat*, right?
And by יום טוב *Yom Tov* you're allowed to cook. And so
for תוספות *Tosafot* it gets off into this question תוספות *Tosafot* is
always asking is, did the מן *man* fall on שבת *Shabbat* or
not? Right, because since you can prepare and do stuff for food
on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, if the פסוקים *pesukim* never say it
didn't fall, which then leads to the question of do you have
שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* on יום טוב *Yom Tov*? Major position in
תוספות *Tosafot* that you might not need שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* on
יום טוב *Yom Tov* because you didn't have a double portion of
the מן *man* on ערב יום טוב *erev Yom Tov*. Anyway, this
is רבא *Rava*'s explanation. Let's just quickly wrap this up. It says
like this: The גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*,
so אביי *Abaye* said to him, אלא מעתה יום טוב בעלמא תשתרי
*ella mei'ata Yom Tov be'alma tishtere*, so okay, but I'm just talking
about a regular יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So I understand that's your
paradigm case of a שבת *Shabbat* preceding יום טוב *Yom Tov*, but
a normal יום טוב *Yom Tov* should be okay because the egg
was finished the day before. No, גזירה משום יום טוב אחר שבת
*gezeirah mishum Yom Tov achar Shabbat*, we're not going to allow any
יום טוב *Yom Tov* because of the scenario of when יום טוב
*Yom Tov* comes after שבת *Shabbat*. שבת בעלמא תשתרי *Shabbat be'alma tishtere*?
Now a normal שבת *Shabbat* should be allowed, which is a little
funny because a normal שבת *Shabbat* the hen is מוקצה *muktzeh*, but
okay. גזירה משום שבת אחר יום טוב *gezeirah mishum Shabbat achar Yom
Tov*. No, because of also we're concerned about the paradigm case of
when שבת *Shabbat* follows יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So basically you're saying
there's this paradigm case of יום טוב *Yom Tov* after שבת *Shabbat*,
our משנה *mishna* doesn't allow even a regular יום טוב *Yom Tov*
as a derivation of that. This is certainly the most complicated explanation.
One more line. ומי גזרינן *umi gazrinan*? Do we really make these
types of גזירות *gezeirot*? והתניא *ve'hatanya*, and here's the question that was
raised: השוחט את התרנגולת ומצא בה ביצים גמורות *hashocheit et hatarnegolles umatzah
bah beitzim gemurot*, you slaughtered a hen on יום טוב *Yom Tov*
and you found completed eggs in the hen, and this presumably was
a hen that was set aside for eating, okay, so again it's
a part of the hen, it's food. מותרות לאוכלן ביום טוב *mutarot
le'ochlam be'Yom Tov*, you can eat them on יום טוב *Yom Tov*.
All right, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, ואי איתא *ve'im issa*, if
you have this idea of רבא *Rava*, that even by a hen
set aside for food, the things have to be prepared from beforehand.
So it sort of says like this, I get that when it's
in the hen it's considered to be part of the hen and
we don't think of it as something different, okay, and therefore you
don't say, oh, a little bit of the hen put on some
fat the day before, it's like a little fat that was put
on, I get why in principle it's allowed because it's not seen
as something new, but if you make גזירות *gezeirot*, לגזר משום הנך
דמתילדי ביומיה *ligzar mishum hanach demisyaldi beyomeia*, so we should make a
גזירה *gezeirah* that you can't eat the eggs inside the hens because
of the eggs that will be laid. And if we don't allow
the laid eggs, we should allow the eggs in the hen. But
it says no, אמר ליה ביצים גמורות במעי אמן מילתא דלא שכיחא
היא *amar lei beitzim gemurot be'mei imman milsa delo shechicha hi*, finding
unlaid eggs in their mother's womb when you slaughter it is something
that is not common, it's not a womb whatever, it's not a
womb, it's not a mammal, מילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו בה רבנן
*milsa delo shechicha lo gazru bei rabbanan* and something that's not common
the רבנן *rabbanan* did not make a גזירה *gezeirah*. So again, although
it's such a complicated explanation of הכנה *hachanah*, it really is a
type of a נולד *nolad*, that if the נולד *nolad* is that
it was something new was created and it was created, you know,
finished being created the day before, and that's a problem when you
have יום טוב *Yom Tov* back with שבת *Shabbat*, but from there
we're going to forbid every case of יום טוב *Yom Tov* even
by itself. A hard explanation both because it makes it a special
case and because the exact idea behind רבא *Rava* preparing automatically not
your own preparing but it being prepared by itself, as Charlie points
out, you're allowed to cook, but you can't have an egg finished.
It's a hard idea, but the גמרא *Gemara* will move on from
this tomorrow to look at yet another explanation. Okay. הדרן עלך *Hadran
Alach*.